<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>History Notes</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2021-04-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Chapter 18</title><link href="/Chapter-18.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Mordy Waldner</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-04-27:/Chapter-18.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Wilmot Proviso&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He proposed to congress that New Mexico, &amp;amp; California should be free
Southerners cried fowl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Popular Sovereignty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;* Its the idea that territories should determine whether or not they were slave states or free states
* It seemed like a good compromise between Abolitionists and Slave Supporters
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;James K. Polk decided …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h1&gt;Wilmot Proviso&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He proposed to congress that New Mexico, &amp;amp; California should be free
Southerners cried fowl&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Popular Sovereignty&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;* Its the idea that territories should determine whether or not they were slave states or free states
* It seemed like a good compromise between Abolitionists and Slave Supporters
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;James K. Polk decided not to run for a second term in 1848
The Democrats nominated Lewis Cask to run for President.
    He supported Popular Sovereignty
This is the last time the Whigs nominated a candidate
    * The Whigs nominated Zachary Taylor
    * He was a general who fought in the Mexican American War
    * He owned slaves
A breakaway party called the Free Soil Party formed.
    * It was made of Dems and Whigs who liked Pop. Sovereignty but didnt like the candidate
    * They were strongly against slavery
        * The Republican party formed out of them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taylor won the election of 1848
Gold was discovered in 1848 in California
It started the Gold Rush
    * The miners brought violence
        * They fought and killed to steal other miners gold
    * And disease
This caused lots of tension
Eventually the miners overran Californias small communities
The Californians decided they wanted to be a state
    * They petitioned Congress for statehood without becoming a territory first
    * They drafted a state constitution
        * It clearly banned slavery in California
        * This was revolutionary
    * Because of this the Southerners didn't allow it to become a state
        * It was left in limbo just like Texas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Harriet Tubman&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She was an escaped slave&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She went back to the south as a spy during the civil war&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After the War she helped slaves escape through the Underground RailRoad&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;She led them to safe houses and they traveled all the way north to Canada or south to Haiti&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Chapter 17: The Mexican American War</title><link href="/Mexican-American-War.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-26T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Mordy Waldner</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-04-26:/Mexican-American-War.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h3&gt;The Mexican American War&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were'nt a lot of spanish ppl in california so they intermarried with the Californian settlers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James K. Polk wanted to acquire Calif. for the U.S except it belonged to Mexico&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polk sent a representative to Mexico w/ 25 million for California
the Mexicans hated …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;The Mexican American War&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were'nt a lot of spanish ppl in california so they intermarried with the Californian settlers&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James K. Polk wanted to acquire Calif. for the U.S except it belonged to Mexico&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polk sent a representative to Mexico w/ 25 million for California
the Mexicans hated the US so much that they declined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polk tried to bait the Mexicans so they would be seen as the aggressor and the US had to defend itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jan 1846:
    Polk ordered Zach Taylor to cross the Rio Grande with 4000 troops into Mexican Territory
    Mexican troops showed up and the 2 armies battled and some Americans were killed
    In May 1846 Polk went to congress and said
    * There were many unpaid claims that mexico owed the US
    * He was angry that the Mexicans refused to meet w/ his representative
    * And finally the Mexicans has American Blood on their hands
    The Mexican American War started in 1846
    Mexico was in no way ready to part with California
    * Both sides were both prepared for war
    * Americans felt Moral Indignation that Mexicans killed Americans
    * Most Americans were pro war
      * They saw Mexico as the agressor
      * Even though it was the US who instigated&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;American Generals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courney
&lt;em&gt; Traveled to Santa Fe
&lt;/em&gt; On the way to Santa Fe he also captured Arizona and New Mexico
Zachary Taylor
&lt;em&gt; Military Genius
&lt;/em&gt; He went from Western Texas to central Mexico
Winfield Scott
&lt;em&gt; Was in the Navy
&lt;/em&gt; He went by sea and made it to Mexico City
Mexico was totally outmatched&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After only 2 years the US came out on top
To add insult to injury the US sent the chief clerk of the State Dept. to make the treaty with Mexico;
not a high ranking official
This went back to the way that Mexico treated Polks Representative
They signed the treaty of Gaudalupe-Hidalgo in 1848
The US bought the land for $15 million
Mexico lost half of its territory
There were Whigs in congress who saw this as a problem
They wanted to know if all the land would be slave land or free land
All the Mexicans who lived in these territories were now all American
This was the war that had the beginings of the anti-war sentiment&lt;/p&gt;</content></entry><entry><title>Chapter 17: Manifest Destiny</title><link href="/chapter17.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2021-04-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-04-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Mordy Waldner</name></author><id>tag:None,2021-04-21:/chapter17.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;h2&gt;William Henry Harrison is elected in 1840&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harrison wasn't the best of leaders so the following 2 men really led the country
 - Daniel Webster was Harrison's secretary of state
 - Henry Clay was leader of the whig party
Harrison made an hour long speech at his inaugauration in the pouring rain …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;William Henry Harrison is elected in 1840&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harrison wasn't the best of leaders so the following 2 men really led the country
 - Daniel Webster was Harrison's secretary of state
 - Henry Clay was leader of the whig party
Harrison made an hour long speech at his inaugauration in the pouring rain and a month later dies in office
Congress had no idea what to do
 - They decided the VP becomes POTUS
John Tyler was now in office&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Clay vs. Tyler&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clay and Webster wanted to pass a bill that would make the bank under Govt. Jurisdiction but Tyler Vetoed it again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A watered down version of the bank bill was also vetoed by Tyler
Eventually Clay and Webster kicked Tyler out of the Whig party telling him hes not a real whig&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Relations with England&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1837 the Canadians wanted indepence from England and the US openly supported the candian rebels&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Caroline&lt;/em&gt; was a US ship carrying weapons to the Canadians
 - The British stopped and searched the ship and sank&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Creole&lt;/em&gt; was a US ship carrying slaves
 - There was a slave rebellion on board and they sailed the ship to british controlled bahamas
 - They were welcomed with open arms adn told they could live as free ppl there&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these 3 events strained the Anglo-American relationship&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skirmishes were starting to break out on the canadian-maine border about where the border line was
Webster and Ash-Burton decided to define the border between Maine and Canada&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Texas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mexico and Mexicans still viewed Texas as a part of Mexico
 - Mexico said to the US that if the US annexed or even recognized Texas it would be viewed as an act of war
Texas was making treaties with Holland, Belgium, and France who recognized Texas as an independent country
England realized that acknowledging Texas would weaken the stability of the US &lt;/p&gt;</content></entry></feed>